Guide to the Madeline Earle Stanton Correspondence
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Madeline Earle Stanton correspondence
1915-1963
1927-1933
Ms Coll 7
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
0.75
(2 boxes)
Madeline Stanton was secretary to Harvey Cushing at the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital in Boston. She accompanied him to Yale in 1933, and after his death, she and John F. Fulton headed the Histiorical Library of the Yale Medical Library. The corresponence consists of letters and cards sent to Madeline Stanton by neurosurgical colleagues and former students of Harvey Cushing, by employees at the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital, and others. Major correspondents include Percival Bailey, Claude S. Beck, Hugh Cairns, Louise Eisenhardt, Eric Oldberg, and Paul Martin. The letters document aspects of Miss Stanton's role as Cushing's secretary and her private life.
Stanton, Madeline E. (Madeline Earle)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Historical Library by Madeline Stanton.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Madeline Earle Stanton Papers (MS 1482), Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Biographical / Historical
Madeline E. Stanton was born in Canton, Massachusetts on June 9, 1898. After graduating cum laude from Smith College in 1919, she was employed as a secretary to Agade Jacchia, conductor of the Boston Pops Orchestra. In 1920, she became secretary to Harvey Cushing, Mosely Professor of Surgery in the Harvard Medical School and surgeon-in-chief of the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital, Boston. She accompanied him to New Haven when he was appointed Sterling Professor of Neurology in 1933. After Cushing's death in 1939, she took a major role in organizing the Historical Library of the Yale Medical Library. She served as Secretary and then Librarian of the Historical Library. She continued to work in the Historical Library beyond her formal retirement in 1968. During her tenure as assistant to Cushing and as Librarian of the Historical Library, Stanton met many neurosurgeons who became long-lasting personal friends. Madeline Stanton died in 1980.
Scope and Contents
The corresponence consists of letters and cards sent to Madeline Stanton by neurosurgical colleagues and former students of Harvey Cushing, by employees at the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital, and others. Major correspondents include Percival Bailey, Claude S. Beck, Hugh Cairns, Louise Eisenhardt, Eric Oldberg, and Paul Martin. The letters document aspects of Madeline Stanton's role as Cushing's secretary and her private life.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence arranged alphabetically. II. Miscellany.
Neurosurgeons; Bailey, Percival, 1892-1973; Beck, Claude S. (Claude Schaeffer), 1894-1971; Cairns, Hugh, Sir, 1896-1952; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; Davey, L. M. (Lycurgus Michael), 1918-; Eisenhardt, Louise, 1891-1967; Henderson, William R.; Horrax, Gilbert, 1887-1957; Martin, Paul; Oldberg, Eric, 1901-1986; Peter Bent Brigham Hospital
- Correspondence, Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged alpabetically by correspondent
  - A (General) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Anrep, G. W., 1930
    - Armitage, George and Mildred, 1930-1931
    - Ashcroft, Peter, 1943
  - Bagdasar, Dimitri, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bailey, Percival, 1925-1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beck, Claude S., 1925-1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - B (General) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Baldy", 1929?
    - Bock, J. S., 1932-1933
    - Bell, Donald C., 1931
    - Bird, Clarence E., n.d.
    - Boyd, Walter W., 1930-1932
    - Bremer, F., 1922
  - Cairns, Hugh, Sir, 1932-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - C (Gerneral) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - C., H. (possibly not Harvey Cushing), n.d.
    - C., Dot, 1928
  - D (General) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Davey, Lycurgus M., 1944 August 11
    - Davidoff, Leo, 1924, 1928
    - De Coppet, Gaston, 1930
    - Dixon, Thomas W., 1929
  - Eisenhardt, Louise, 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fulton, Lucia (Mrs. John Fulton), 1929-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Grant, Francis C., 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - G (General) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Glenn, Frank, 1931-1932
    - Grosz, Emile de (includes book of images of Budapest), n.d.
    - Gruder, R. luc, n.d.
    - Gutierrez-Mahoney, C. G. de, 1963
  - Henderson, William R. ("Willie"), 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Horrax, Gilbert, 1923-1928 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - H & I (General) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Herrmann, Louis, n.d.
    - Howland, Dr. (secretary to), 1935
    - Ingraham, Frank, n.d.
  - J (General) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - James, William, 1922
    - Jefferson, Geoffrey, n.d.
  - K (General) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Keller, Allen D., 1931
    - Klebs, Arnold C., 1936
  - L (General) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Lindau, Arvid, 1932
    - Leriche, René (stamp removed from envelope), 1929?
    - Locke, C. E., Jr., 1922
    - Light, Richard U. (holiday card), n.d.
  - Martin, Paul, 1920-1931 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - M (General) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - MacLean, Paul and Alison, 1956
    - Marshall, 1930
    - Mayo, William, 1931
    - McLean, A. J., 1930-1932
    - "Mildred", 1930
    - Morrelle, Jean ( stamp has been removed from envelope), 1926, 1930
  - Oldenberg, Eric, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - P-R (General) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Powers, John H., 1931
    - Russell, Dorothy, 1928
  - S (General) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Scarff, John H., 1932
    - Schreiber, Frederic, 1929-1930
    - Seaver?, John E., 1930
    - Shea, Mary M., 1932
    - Streeter, Alice (Mrs. Edward C. Streeter), 1947-1948
    - Strong, Robert C., 1932
  - T-W (General) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Tanaka, Fumio., 1928-1929
    - Teel, Harold M., 1929
    - Wheeler, D. W., 1922
  - Unidentified correspondents - letters, 1924-1933 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Unidentified correspondents - postcards, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Miscellany, 1933 & n.d.; Series II
  - Photographs (4), labeled, of places in the Far East and Europe (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Brochure about the World Fair, Chicago, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Receipts from Smith College (with later note by Madeline Stanton), 1915-1917 (Box 2, Folder 29)